Good week everybody, good חודש, Chodesh, ראש חודש שבט, Rosh Chodesh Shevat,
look out the window it looks like it's two weeks away from
ט״ו בשבט, Tu Bishvat, you know, so with all the snow though
it'll be probably like 50 degrees in like two days or something.
Anyway, we start מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah Zarah, which is like
the last large מסכת masechet in נזיקין, Nezikin, we're getting close to
ending נזיקין. Nezikin. And what is עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah about? It
is not about the act of worshipping idols, believe it or not.
It is primarily, I would say it's split, but fundamentally
or certainly the first half of it is devoted to how do
we negotiate the larger world around us especially given that that larger
world is not only not Jewish, but also a pagan world. And
that is certainly the focus of the first two chapters. To some
degree it's about idolaters, rather it is, it's about idolaters. Interesting the
first משנה, mishna, our line opens, לפני אידיהם, Lifnei edeihem, before the
holidays of, if you look at the word in the משנה mishna
it's עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, but actually the original text was של
גוים, shel goyim, okay, but
and in general I should say that, you know, if you ask
a normal person who has learned at ישיבה, yeshiva, what is the
standard word in the גמרא gemara that refers to non-Jews, they'll say
עכום, akum, which is an abbreviation of עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, ovdei kochavim
u'mazalot, a worshiper of stars and the constellations or whatever. But actually
the word in the גמרא, gemara, in the משנה, mishna, in the
ברייתא braita is either גוים goyim or נכרי, nochri, right, which is
a foreigner, nations, it's not about idolaters. What happened was, I've mentioned
this before but might as well mention this right up at the
start, that in the Middle Ages when Jews, there were these Jews
who converted to Christianity, apostates, they told the church about all of
the negative stuff that was in the תלמוד Talmud about attitudes towards
non-Jews, and that led to the תלמוד, Talmud, that led to the
church at various places
confiscating, censoring, and even burning the תלמוד. Talmud. So Jews went through
a process of self-censorship, where they took out all the time it
said the word גוי goy or נכרי nochri and they replaced it
with the word עכום akum so that they could say to the
church, and sometimes they actually took things out, like we had in
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, took out passages relating to Jesus and so on, took
out whole passages. But primarily it just replaced the word גוי goy
or נכרי nochri with the word עכום akum so they could say
to the church, this is not referring to you, this is referring
to the ancient pagans. And you know that a source is very
offensive if they don't even use the word עכום akum but they
use the word like כנעני, Knani, a Canaanite, because then they could
really say this was just referring to those ancient people from thousands
of years ago. So the discussion in the גמרא gemara for example
of גזל גוי, gezel goy, are you allowed to steal from a
non-Jew, in our גמרא gemara it appears as גזל כנעני, gezel Knani,
can you steal from a Canaanite? Okay, so you know that you're
dealing with an offensive passage when the word is כנעני. Knani. Anyway,
so it is true that there is a difference, not all non-Jews
are idolaters and even if pretty much they all were, most of
them were at the time of the rabbis, it's not all because
of their status of idolaters, sometimes it's just the fact that they're
non-Jews. So there really is a difference between the word גוי goy
and עכום, akum, you know, עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. Nevertheless,
there is, you know, living in a pagan world, there was not
a one-to-one correspondence, but a high degree of overlap. So even for
example in the first משנה mishna where it's לפני אידיהם של גוים,
Lifnei edeihem shel goyim, the problem is you can't do certain types
of interactions with the non-Jew on and before their holidays because of
its connection to idolatry. So even though the original word was גוי,
goy, it was you know just
non-Jew, Gentile, it was with an assumption that Gentiles equaled idolatry, you
know, clearly that was the standard. But nevertheless, it's important to know
that sometimes the concern is their pagan worship and sometimes the concern
is just that they're non-Jews, and there are sometimes as we will
see, the גמרא gemara acknowledges non-Jews who are not idolaters, who are
not pagans. So back to the point, so the primary concern of
the first two chapters is interacting with the Gentile pagan world. Sometimes
that concern is that you will indirectly support or participate in or
be connected to their idolatry or pagan practices or you know pagan
holidays, so it's about עבודה זרה avodah zarah concerns. Sometimes it's concerns
about other types of things, about ways in which the תלמוד Talmud
sort of saw the Gentiles around them as being sexually promiscuous,
ways in which they saw them as being as you know as
because obviously they had suffered through the Hadrianic persecution or whatever, you
know, as being a type of a hostile people, you know, that
they were hostile towards the Jews and maybe even would seek opportunities
to kill Jews, you know, so that becomes very interesting in terms
of what is as we're going to read, how much of this
is factually accurate and how much of this is a perception that
an oppressed minority, the Jews, have
towards. And how much does that lead to a certain type of
a perception of what are those dangers that the outside world presents.
And sometimes the concerns are going to be the ones that actually
we still have today, which are much more tame types of concerns,
but nevertheless very real and pervasive, which is buying foodstuff from them
and how much do you have to be concerned about non-kosher products.
You know, this was before the world of הכשרים *hechsherim*, right? So
what products can you buy from them? Do you have to be
concerned either absolutely non-kosher like maybe they have some חזיר *chazar* in
a product, you know, some pork, and maybe it's a problem because
some things of theirs were connected to idolatry. So that's the first
two chapters that negotiating that larger world, and then that turns us
to what we're going to get in the final two chapters, there
are five chapters, is a hyper-focus on one particular area of their
food, which is, any guesses? Cheese? No, no. Wine! So the last
two chapters are all about the wine issue and what type of
circumstances makes the wine, you know, problematic through their touch, through whatever,
and so on. So that's like the final two chapters. The middle
chapter is the one that has the most to do with idolatry
per se, and the middle chapter is the one about if you
find their, you know, their idols discarded or, you know, various types
of like dishes and bowls—like if anybody ever went to the Metropolitan,
you know, you see those things—right, which of those things are things
that are sort of maybe things that were worshipped and therefore forbidden,
you know, if they have pictures of their gods on it, does
that mean it was an object of worship or does that—is that
just a decoration? Right, so the middle chapter deals with the actual
concern of idols or objects of worship. Okay, but the first two
is general navigating that larger pagan gentile world and the ways in
which we might, you know, are we participating in it, are we
being endangered physically or religiously through certain types of interactions and so
on. And the last two is about their wine, and the middle
one is about objects that might be objects of worship. Okay, so
it's a quite fascinating מסכת *masekhet*. I think both in terms of,
you know, for like historians it's fascinating because it gives you a
window into the realities of the Rabbis and the world in which
they lived, and we see a lot of reference to, you know,
pagan Roman types of things, so it's just fascinating to get that
type of window into that reality. And I think that it's very
halakhically relevant because of all the issues relating to wine and all
the issues relating to food and all these types of things, you
know, the cheese, the milk, things that are cooked by non-Jews, etc.
And it's also I think religiously philosophically fascinating because it's a question
about how do we perceive the outside world, how do we understand
the degree to which we have to separate ourselves from it or
can integrate ourselves into it as long as we take certain safeguards
and precautions, how are
non-Jews perceived by the Rabbis, how is the non-Jewish world perceived by
the Rabbis, so it's a lot of interesting things that come up
in this tractate. Because of the practical aspects, you do have a
lot of ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim* on this tractate. A lot of the
classic ראשונים Rishonim, *rishonim*, you know, that you did not have in
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* or you didn't have in שבועות *Shavuot*, you have in
עבודה זרה avoda zara. *Avodah Zarah* because there's so much practical aspects
to this tractate. You had a question.
Is there a ירושלמי Yerushalmi. *Yerushalmi* also?
Yes, there is.
So is there a different psychology that when they're still in the
land and it's our land, it's a different approach to... Yes.
So that's a very good question. First of all, we will find
that there are certain issues that come up specifically relating to Jewish
versus non-Jewish presence in the land of Israel, which is not just
a question of how do we perceive non-Jews, but how do we
sort of what are we trying to do to protect
Jewish societies and Jewish, you know, sort of industry and, you know,
presence in the land of Israel, certain things might be very much
to try to, you know, so that's one aspect of like our
sort of our presence and our self-sufficiency and so on in the
land of Israel. The general question of how do you look at
the non-Jews and how hostile do you look at them and so
on, you know, and so first of all, yes, the experience in
בבל *Bavel* was very different. In בבל *Bavel*, the Jews had it
good, the government was a sort of by and large a sort
of a welcoming, supportive type of a government. In Israel, the Roman
government, you know, they had a lot of history of oppression and
so on and, you know, there was a feeling also that maybe
in the—outside of Israel, you're being hosted by another nation and they're
like welcoming hosts, whereas within the Israel, inside the land of Israel,
these Romans are invading our land and are oppressing us in our
land and, you know, whatever. So it's a very different type of
a dynamic. Now, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* and the ברייתא *Baraita*, which
everything is the point of departure, was all written in the land
of Israel. But in terms of how then it gets dealt with
in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* itself, I have not done
a—yes, what you're saying is very reasonable. and I'm sure that scholars
have looked at it. I have not done like a rigorous sort
of side-by-side comparison of them.
My sense is, my sense is, yeah, I know, maybe it's actually
a good time to go back to the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, maybe it's
an excellent time maybe, maybe I actually will try to do that.
That's a good suggestion. But I will say that I think that
from what, you know,
my... what I... I do not sort of off the top of
my head remember going through מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah in
the בבלי Bavli that a different... that you got a sort of
a different type of an approach emerging from it than was present
already in the Tannaic material. Meaning elsewhere you have a very different
approach that emerges from the בבלי Bavli about attitudes towards the sort
of non-Jewish, you know, government and so on. For example, the principle
that דינא דמלכותא דינא, Dina de'malchuta dina, the law of the government
is the law, the law of the kingdom is the law, is
articulated in the בבלי, Bavli, it's never articulated in the ירושלמי.
The משנה Mishnah basically treats like tax collectors as all thieves, whereas
the... because, you know, that's how it was perceived of in Israel,
whereas the בבלי Bavli says, why are they thieves? They have a
license to do it from the government and it's a legal thing
and so on, and it re-reads... like, you know, or can you
swear falsely to a... somebody who's there to collect a import tariff,
you know? So the basically the משנה Mishnah, sort of says yes,
exactly how it gets around violating an oath, whatever, but you can
sort of misrepresent yourself, and the בבלי Bavli says how you allowed
to misrepresent yourself? The law of the government is the law. So,
you know, that's where it's very clearly that difference comes out. Off
the top of my head I can't recall that it's so clear
in terms of how the בבלי Bavli deals with this tractate, but
let's keep our eyes open for that. Okay, so with that in
mind, let's get started. All right? So here comes... and we're right
at the very beginning, we're going to jump immediately into an Aggadic
section after we get through the משנה, Mishnah which actually will start
giving us a sense of how did we perceive that larger pagan
Gentile world. Okay, so לפני אידיהן של גוים, Lifnei eydeihem shel goyim,
before the holidays of the non-Jews,
שלושה ימים, shlosha yamim, starting three days before, אסור לשאת ולתת עמהם,
asur laset velatet imahem, you can't do business with them, like buying
and selling, ולהשאילן, ul'hashilan, to lend them objects, ולשאול מהם, ulish'ol mehem,
or to borrow objects from them, ולהלוותם, ul'halvotam, to lend them money,
וללוות מהם, ulilovot mehem, or to borrow money from them, ולפרען, ul'faran,
to pay up a debt that you owe them, ולפרוע מהם, ulifroa
mehem, or to get them to pay a debt up to you
during this period. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, נפרעין מהם, nifrain
mehem, מפני שמצר הוא לו, mipnei shemeitzer hu lo, you can actually
have them... get them to pay up a debt because that's an
anguish to them, you know, they feel like, oh my God, like
I had to give that guy the thousand dollars I owed him.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him, אף על פי
שמצר הוא עכשיו שמח הוא לאחר זמן. af al pi shemeitzer hu
achshav same'ach hu le'achar zman. Yes, he might feel bad now, but
in the end he, you know, you know, he feels good that
he finally, you know, paid up his debt, he's done with his
mortgage, he finally paid off his student loan. You know, people there's
a satisfaction that you know that you're free from that, even though
it meant shelling out money. So it is not clear from here
what the problem is. You have a hint... why is there a
problem doing business beforehand? You have a hint from the fact that
they're debating in the end whether is this something that causes sadness
and anguish or something that causes joy. So somehow there's a sense
that something that causes joy is a problem. Now, why?
Yeah, but certainly they don't do, because I mean they'd be happy
any other day as well.
Well, right, it's not like you're אסור assur to cause joy to
non-Jews, but why... so right, why is that an issue connected to
their holiday? So we are going to see a couple of reasons.
If you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi gives a
simple reason, I mean I don't mean it's simple trivial, but whatever,
you know, it... but anyway, but...
it simplifies like some more complex thing that you have in the
גמרא. Gemara If you look at רש"י, Rashi, the first second line,
וכולן משום דאזיל ומודי לעבודת כוכבים ביום אידו. vechulan mishum de'azil u'modeh
l'avoda kochavim beyom eydo.
All of these are forbidden because it will lead the non-Jew to
be happy, and then when they go to celebrate on their holiday,
three, two, one days later, they will actually be happier on their
holiday, and not only happier so you're increasing their happiness in their
holiday, but they will מודה, modeh, they will give thanks to their
god. Thank you Zeus for helping me have that good business deal.
Thank you Zeus for allowing me to borrow the thousand dollars I
needed from the non-Jew, from the Jew. Thank you for allowing me
to finally pay off that debt that I owed the Jew. So
you will indirectly therefore support their עבודה זרה. avoda zara, Now, that's
one explanation.
Even in that explanation, the question to ask is, and why is
that a problem? Right? Why is it a problem that they are
going to thank their god? So the... the fundamental explanation given in
the גמרא Gemara is, why do you think that would be a
problem?
You're abetting idolatry.
Okay, so non-Jews, the שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvot bnei Noach,
are also forbidden to do... to worship idols and to do עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah? and you are encouraging them, so it's a type
of a לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, or even if it's not לפני
עיוור, lifnei iver, לפני עיוור lifnei iver is more limited to when
like they really needed you in order to do this, but somehow
you
are
helping... If it's
only
because we're concerned for their sins, it's also a problem for us
to aid and abet their sins, right? But the problem focuses on
the fact that a sin—they are doing a sin—and we don't want
to aid and abet that, yes.
I'm just thinking like if you were to go shopping like on
Christmas Eve and buy a bunch of presents, it looks like you're
going to be giving to kids, right? Like you're participating in the
culture that seems to be surrounding the holiday.
Excellent. So what I think is, and I think it's fascinating the
way the גמרא Gemara almost like ignores this possibility, but to me
this is almost like the much more obvious explanation is, not that
I am concerned with—it starts with they're doing a sin and I'm
aiding their
sin—but how much am I connected to the world of עבודה זרה?
Avodah Zarah And you could say that two ways. The way Jenna
is saying it, which is maybe even the more direct way, which
I totally agree with, is you're being part of all of the
excitement leading up to it. Imagine if it's three days
before—just we know about the idea of a Christmas season, right?—so if
there's going to be a lot of shopping and a lot of
stuff and a lot of business being done leading up to this
major day, and you're going out and you're doing, interacting with them,
even in interacting in relatively neutral ways. It's one thing to do
shopping if you know, but why is it an issue? And so
lending money you can understand. Hey, can I borrow a thousand dollars?
I got my Christmas gift list to whatever. Not saying that Christianity
is עבודה זרה—different avodah zarah. discussion—it's just as the phenomenon we're used
to. But if you lend them money, you understand that you're helping
them. You lend them objects, maybe they're using those objects in their
actual—but why is it a problem to borrow money from them? Why
is it a problem to borrow objects? And the point is, okay,
technically speaking
you might not be assisting them, but because of this—this is the
whole environment going on. People are lending, people are borrowing, people are
doing this, right? So you're playing, you are being part of all
of the busyness and the excitement that's around it, that is a
problem that you are connecting yourself to that pagan type of a—idolatrous
type of a culture. So I definitely think that that is the
simple
explanation. Now, so since between two pagans, right, one of them is
borrowing and one is lending, the lender is not
actually—whatever. Anyway, my point is even if you're borrowing, this pagan is
lending you something and you're borrowing from it, that's not helping him
in his idolatry that he's lending you something, right? But nevertheless, since
what's going on in the whole environment is borrowing and lending and
all this type of stuff, you become part of that. So that's
certainly I think the more straightforward explanation. It's interesting that the גמרא
Gemara does not say that. A variation of that, a little bit
closer, viewing a little closer to what the גמרא's Gemara point is
that they're worshipping, is my concern with me, with his worship, is
not that I'm aiding and abetting his worship, but that through him,
it's sort of like I'm also connected to that act of worship.
So it's sort of the difference of like of like לפני עיוור
Lifnei Iver and, like if I see somebody being
מחלל שבת, Mechalel Shabbos, right, and I—whatever, I'm trying to think of
like a good
example—okay, let's say somebody there is cooking on שבת Shabbos and I'm
standing by while they're in their kitchen cooking on שבת Shabbos and
I'm talking to them and I'm tasting the food and I'm like—whatever—and
I'm not doing anything אסור, assur, right? So is the problem that
I'm helping them do their sin, or that I'm participating in it?
Participating, not actually transgressing, but to some degree participating, right? So I
think that's another way of looking at it, that if we want
to focus on the fact that because of this interaction the pagan
goes, this idolatry goes and worships idols, how much do I—am I
a little bit participating in what they're doing? Not because of their
sin, but it connects me to what's being done. So I think
that there's that's a range of different ways of looking at what
the issue is. One is sort of the narrow way that the
גמרא Gemara, looks at it: it's their sin and am I aiding
and abetting their sin? And from that perspective, if non-Jews were not
prohibited against worshipping idols, there would be nothing wrong with what I
was doing, right? That's a good way of testing that it all
starts with their sin. The other problem is no, it's yes, it's
about their sin, but it's not about I'm concerned of aiding them,
I'm concerned that it makes it like a little bit like I'm
connected to an act. act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. And then
the third, which so those are variations on a theme, but the
third approach is what Jenna said, which I agree to me is
what the one I would like to say because it's the more
פשט, pshat, is how much when this is all that's going on
at this time, this type of stuff connected to the holiday, even
when I do it in a way that's not connected to the
holiday, does it wind up that I am now participating in that
type of a culture? And again, the problem not because of their
sin, but because it connects me to the big, you know, pagan
event that's happening. Yes.
I know we're going to address the Sunday issue. Yes, I'm not
getting that back. But we're also trying to remember,
they have now the big sale, right? It's going to cost me
ten, fifty percent more if I go on other days. Is that
taken into account? Right.
So, because you asked that, I don't know if that was your
intentional but a perfect segue into discussing this larger תוספות Tosafot here
because a major issue and I guess I'll say it upfront and
we'll discuss it more as it comes up, but a major issue
that comes up in the ראשונים Rishonim is that in the Christian
countries, the major market day was Sunday. And Christianity was looked at
as עבודה זרה. avodah zarah Okay, it still is according many many
areas of הלכה halacha and so on, depends if it's עבודה זרה
avodah zarah for us, עבודה זרה avoda zara? for them, whatever. It's
a separate conversation. Let's just put that out there right now. So
therefore the question was, how do and but Sunday was the big
market day and that was their holiday, as it were. How are
we able to do business on their, on their holiday? Isn't that
exactly a violation of this? So there was a range of different
answers to this. So for example, take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
this is important because this is talk about negotiating the larger world
in which they lived. This problem continued in the period of the
ראשונים, it wasn't just a period for the rabbis an issue for
the rabbis of the תלמוד. Talmud. So if you take a look
at תוספות Tosafot here has a couple of answers. His first answer
is
let's first read the question. He says
תוספות Tosafot אסור, Assur, he says וקשה, ve-kasha,
it's the lines that start with על. al. It's one, two, four
lines under the word
אסור. Assur. על מה סמכו העולם לשאת ולתת ביום איד עובדי כוכבים
עמהם? Al ma samchu ha-olam lases u-lases beyom eid ovdei kochavim imahem?
Why are we allowed to do business with them on their holiday?
נהי דרוב אידיהם מן הקדושים הם, Nihi de-rov eideihem min ha-kadoshim hem,
although most of their holidays are from the קדושים. kadoshim. Anybody know
what that means?
Saints. Most of theirs are saint days, right? So Saint Patrick's Day,
saint days. Okay, and therefore he's saying maybe a saint day isn't
an actual holiday because a saint day is about a saint and
they don't treat their saints as gods, which תוספות Tosafot sort of
points out, right? They're holy people but they're not, so it's not
actually a worship of their god, as it were. Okay, it's a
saint day. מכל מקום בכל שבוע יום אחד יש להם. Mikol makom
be-chol shavuah yom echad yesh lahem. Every week they have one day,
Sunday, and that is their real religious holiday and therefore how do
we do business on their Sunday? Okay, so he has a couple
of answers. So one answer
is לכך נראה. le-kach nireh. You go down to the line that
starts with the word נראה, nireh, about ten lines under where we
were reading. דשרי משום איבה. De-shari mishum eivah. It's permissible so as
not to engender their hatred. If we wouldn't do business with them,
they would have you know, there's this concern of viewing the Gentiles
around us as always
potentially hostile. As always there's maybe antisemitism right under the surface, we
don't want to trigger it. That's a particular way of looking at
the world in which you live, that there's always this איבה eivah
concern, this concern of hatred, so we don't want to trigger that.
Now, the problem with that answer is תוספות Tosafot says look, I
get how if they come to you to buy something and you
say I can't sell you something, I can't lend you money, you're
going to trigger their hatred. But how about if you just don't
go to the market on Sunday? They're not going to be upset
if they don't see you in the market. Why do they know
why you're not coming to the market? So he's not happy with
the answer of איבה, eivah, although a number of ראשונים do say
no, if all the Jews stop coming to the market, they're going
to be really annoyed, they're losing out a major segment of whatever
and they want to use the explanation of איבה. eivah. The first
by the way, to pause though, it starts with and this is
often how תוספות Tosafot operates, he's not saying, okay, nobody's going to
the market but I have to find a way to allow people
to go to the market on Sunday. No. Everybody's going to the
market in apparent violation of this prohibition. I now have to figure
out how to justify the behavior that they're already doing. So one
explanation is not to engender their hatred. Another explanation, which is the
flip side of איבה, eivah, is דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Not I
sort of say like, oh, I'm afraid they're going to want to
do bad things to me if I don't, but if we're living
among them, we have to act in ways that
encourage positive that cultivate
positive interactions. And therefore this is the right way to interact with
the non-Jews amongst whom we live is to participate in these types
of days. So it's sort of framing it in a pragmatic type
of a way. we really shouldn't be doing it, but you know
whatever, but it's rather than sort of seeing them as potentially hostile,
it's more focusing on a positive value of cultivating positive interactions.
A slight variation of this is if you take a look
at, and here he quotes the ירושלמי, one minute, gets wide.
Okay, yes, thank you, four lines down where it gets wide in
the middle where it says אי נמי, Inami, he says, אי נמי,
Inami, יש לסמוך, yesh lismoch, we can rely אהא דתני בירושלמי aha
d'tani b'Yerushalmi אמתניתין, amatnitin, which we taught דאסור לשאת ולתת עמהם, d'asur
laseit ulatet imahem, you can't do business with
them. תני במדרש, tani bamedrash, when is this true? בעובדי כוכבים שאינו
מכירו, b'ovdei kochavim she'eino makiro, if it's a non-Jew who's a stranger,
so don't do business. אבל בעובדי כוכבים שמכירו aval b'ovdei kochavim she'makiro
מותר, mutar, but if he's not a stranger, you know who he
is, it's allowed to do business on their holidays מפני שהוא כמחניף,
mipnei she'hu k'machanif, it's like flattering them. What does that mean? ותני,
v'tani, we taught הנכנס לעיר ומצא שמחים שמח עמהם hanichnas l'ir u'matza
simchim sameach imahem שאינו אלא כמחניף. she'eino ela k'machanif. If you go
into a city and everybody is rejoicing, they're in the middle of
celebrating some holiday of Zeus or whatever, you can actually and they
say, here, have a drink, you can't say, oh, I can't have
a drink or whatever, it's better to say, no, take a drink,
because that's like flattering them. So that's first of all is like
shocking that you can do, do some form, I mean, you're not
worshipping the god, but some form of rejoicing, you know, singing along
with them, they put their arm around you and they want to
sing or they give you a drink and you're allowed to do
it because it's like flattering. Now, what's flattering mean? So one way
of understanding flattering is it's a type of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom,
you want to get along with them. Okay, but I think the
other part of what flattering here means is it's like, you know,
and this I wrote I wrote this up around Christmas time about
like giving Christmas gifts or whatever, going to Christmas parties, you know,
and so on, if it's not blatantly religious, is that they understand
that you're just sort of, you know, being like a decent person
and, you know, just because you're, you know, giving somebody a Christmas
gift and saying Merry Christmas, it doesn't mean that you, that you
celebrate Christmas, right? It means you're just being a, you're doing the,
the right neighborly, nice, polite type, polite type of a thing, right?
This is the polite way in which you interact. So if you
go ahead and give a, you're being, you're being polite and neighborly,
like somebody was actually saying to me like, you know, what do
you think about kids going on
trick-or-treat? I say I think it's really a problem, it's really אסור
assur because of the חוקותיהם. chukoseihem. So they said, well, what do
you think about if trick-or-treat kids come to you, can you give
them candy? I say, of course, that's just being a good neighbor.
You know, so it's like, you know, so like saying, you know,
Merry Christmas and giving somebody a Christmas gift or whatever, you're just
being polite and a good neighbor and so on. I think that's
what מחניף machanif means. Okay, so it's saying, you know, somebody says,
here, have a drink, you know, and you, because you're in the,
you walked into the middle of their party for Zeus and you
take a drink, you're just being polite.
You're not exactly, so then you can't sing with Zeus holiday songs.
Well, maybe.
The question is where exactly do you draw that line? But anyway,
so that's a series of explanations which are yes to problem, but
because of the realities amongst the non-Jews who we live, they're potentially
hostile, or we want to foster positive interactions, or people understand that
it's a type of a, of a politeness and, you know, and
they don't really, it's not really read as a direct support, you
know, all those are reasons why we can give more latitude. Yes,
Jenna.
I'm just confused about these two examples, right? The one is where
you know the person, yes, but then it gives the example of
arriving in a city, which to me is about you're there, you
don't know anyone, you're like essentially dangerous, right? Like if you come
in as a stranger, make yourself stand out. Oh, okay, so have
a drink so no one like thinks about you too much. But
then the one where you know them, that seems like we, I
feel like we would be more worried about that because they're close,
you're close to them maybe.
Right, so the concern about are we getting too close to them,
which is sort of framed under the rubric of בנותיהם, bnoseihem, right,
that's not the concern here. Um, I think the difference is is
that in one case you're, once you're in the middle of something,
to extract yourself from it is like, you know, and to say
no and to reject is a, is a problem, you're pushing it
away and there there's that sense of מחניף, machanif, flattering, however you
define it, I'll just, I'll call it politeness, which is by saying,
by once you find yourself, oh my god, I walked in and
they're in middle of the celebration, right, there's some type of rudeness
by refusing. Whereas in terms of doing business, right, it's not like
I'm excusing myself from something, I'm actually going to do business with
you, right, so if you're a stranger or, you know, whatever, it's,
I can say no without being rude. If you're a friend, right,
then and you ask to borrow money from me or, you know,
why am I not coming, I normally come to your store whatever,
there's more of a rudeness even when I don't show up, you
know, so I think the question is like what scenarios have that
rudeness and it depends on the situation. Anyway, the last, so, so
those are a series of answers which have often been
Another answer is, I'm saving the best answer for last. Another answer
is רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* says and he goes into details I
won't get into, that really the only problem with doing business, maybe
loans is a different issue, but the only problem with doing business,
buying and selling, he says is specifically when you sell them objects
that they could directly use in their pagan celebrations. But to sell
objects that they can't use in their pagan celebrations is not a
problem. But then he's got an issue, and this is again, it's
always fascinating when they bring in their historical reality. Look at the
bottom of תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*. You see the word he says להטבותם
*lehatvotam*
and if you go up three lines above up, he says like
this. ולפי פירוש רבנו תם *ulephi peirush Rabbeinu Tam*, if people see
where I am, three lines above the word להטבותם *lehatvotam* beginning of
the line, אין לתמוה מנהג העולם *ein litmoha minhag ha’olam*. According to
רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* that the whole problem is to sell them
objects that they might use directly in their worship, you don't have
to be astounded about the practice, שאפילו אם היו מחזיקים אותם כעובדי
עבודת כוכבים *she’aphilu im hayu makhzikim otam ke’ovdei avodat kokhavim*, even if
we were to treat Christians as עובדי עבודת כוכבים *ovdei avodat kokhavim*,
as people who do עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah*, this is
the question we're going to get back to later right, שהרי אינם
עושים שום תקרובת *sheharei einam osim shum tikrovet*. When the things we
sell them, they don't use them as a type of an offering,
as a sacrifice. They don't actually, you know, bring these objects as
a sacrifice. Okay, and then he says אלא במעות *ela bama’ot*. No,
actually the one thing that they offer as an offering is money,
when they put the money in the, in the you know, plate
that they pass around. That is their act of offering. So he
says, ah, but if that's their offering, why can we buy objects
from them? We're giving them money and then they're going to use
the money to put up on their plate. ובזה לא שייך חורבך
והרבה מעות מצויים להם לאותו דבר *uvize lo shayakh chorvakh ve’harbeh ma’ot
metzuyim lahem le’oto davar*. He says but you know what, like money
is fungible. It's like just because we sold them some stuff and
they have some money, it's not like oh, now I have something
I can put on the plate when it goes around and beforehand
I didn't. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* is basically says one way
of saying it is the whole problem of selling is that they're
going to use the object directly as a type of an offering
and therefore that's not a concern for us. So that's a very
helpful narrow way of explaining why it's not a problem. And then
it's, here's a fascinating little like historical like ריאליה *realia* insight. He
says ומיהו נכון הוא להחמיר כשבא עובד כוכבים ואומר ve-omer הלויני מעות
לשקרי *umihu nakhon hu lehachmir keshebah oved kokhavim ve’omer halveini ma’ot leshikri*.
When some, when the non-Jew comes and says lend me money for
my, and then here you get how the Jews would like euphemize
or whatever, there's an opposite word for euphemize, which is to use
a bad term for something. I forgot what that word is. Anyway,
when they're referring to certain, you know, rituals or things of the
Christians. So when they say lend me money for my falsehood, obviously
they're not saying for my falsehood, שקורין אופריר *shekorin operier*. I think
that's the Pope. Somebody basically wants to borrow money, you know, for
like, you know, maybe the Pope is raising money for the next
crusade or something. Okay, so he says you shouldn't do that. Because,
you know, then you really are giving them, contributing money, you're lending
them money that they're going to use in some ritual thing and
they're exactly saying I need to borrow this money for some religious
purpose. אבל רבנו חננאל אמר כי גם באותם אופריר *aval Rabbeinu Chananel
amar ki gam be’otam operier*, I have to find exactly what the
אופריר *operier* is, אין שום איסור *ein shum issur*. I don't think
it's exactly Pope because you'll see, כי מה שהם נותנים אותם לגלחים
ולכומרים *ki mah shehem notnim otam lagalachim ulekhomarim*, the fact that they
give that money, it doesn't mean Pope, it means something else. The
fact that they give that money to their priests and to their
monks, אינו ממש לשם עבודת כוכבים אלא לצורך הנאתם *eino mamash leshem
avodat kokhavim ela letzorekh hana’atam*. They're not worship using it directly in
their acts of worship. They're just using it to support, like, you
know, to pay for the monks' food and their lodging and whatever.
So to support the actual, you know,
practitioners and not to be used directly in an act of worship
is not itself a problem. So you see how תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
is sort of trying to navigate this complicated reality. Jews here for,
at the end of this, we're no longer talking about before their
holidays. We're talking about the fact that they were in the business
of money lending. And what happens if the local church comes to
you and wants to borrow money? Are you allowed to use to
lend them money? So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* basically says ideally not and
then he says you know what you can. Because if they're just
using the money for operate, not well I guess operating expenses, but
if they're using the money you know for the food and lodging
of their, of the monks and whatever, then that's not really directly
going, it's only very indirect. It's not going to the people, it's
not going to the actual acts of worship itself. Okay, so here
you've got, I'm saving the best for last. One set of explanations
which are it's all okay, it's okay because it really is a
problem, but you know we got to get along with them or
it's only being polite, it's not being rude, etc. Another explanation is
technically speaking
this is not really helping them in their acts of worship. The
money isn't helping them. You know when you do business it's not
helping them. And the money, it's going to the priest, it's not
going to the act of worship, so technically speaking, it just, it
avoids the exact transgression. The most interesting answer is the one that
I've been holding back, which is maybe we have to stop thinking
about priests and Christians as עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avoda zara. Is
this really עבודה זרה? avoda zara Now, one way you could say
this, it's not idolatry, Christianity isn't idolatry, you know, they believe in
a single God, etc. That's a conversation we could have some other
time, and it's not the conversation that תוספות Tosafoses has. תוספות Tosafos
assumes that Christianity is עבודה זרה. avoda zara The basic reason it
was assumed is because it's important to say at the outset that
עבודה זרה avoda zara is not specifically, what do you call it,
idolatry. עבודה זרה avoda zara means primarily two things: either the worship
of a different god, or the use of images in the worship
of a god. And the basic reason that Christianity was seen as
עבודה זרה avoda zara. is because both of those issues come up.
Number one is, you know, some people say, oh, Christianity is עבודה
זרה avoda zara, because the Trinity was considered to be polytheism. That's
nonsense. Nobody ever said the Trinity was polytheism, but what people said
was the idea of three that is one and the idea of
a Trinity, that's not the God that we worship. That is some
completely different idea of God, meaning the Muslims might have a different
story about God. They believe that God's prophet was, you know, Muhammad,
God's chosen son was Ishmael. That's a different story, but we recognize
the God that they're worshipping. The God of a Trinity, the God
who takes human form, who takes, you know, the incarnated form, whatever
of God, that is a complete different idea of God that is
so foreign to the one that we think. Yes, there are different
ideas about what God is, but that is seen as like a
different God. It's actually interesting, תוספות Tosafos in one place says, actually
the God, the Father of the Christians is the same God. It's
when it's the other parts of the Trinity which are a different
god. Okay, but it's not about poly, it's not about the number,
it's about is it understood to be a different, you know, a
different god? And the other part about it is that they do
use, you know, images, whatever, especially before the Reformation, right? And yes,
there was a difference between Western Christianity and Eastern Orthodox, but anyway,
all of the use of the statues and the images and so
on. So even, you know, and how much is worshipping God through
those things? Or, part of that was the whole מחלוקת machlokes of
Western Christianity and Eastern Orthodox. Was these actually had power, these images,
or were they just for edification and inspiration purposes? Anyway, so תוספות
Tosafos is not prepared to say that he doesn't consider Christianity עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. But what he says, and this is one of
the foundational תוספות Tosafos in how we begin to modify our approach
to Christians and Christianity, is that maybe we don't look at the
Christians as really being עובדי עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now, what does
that mean? The problem is that this becomes a little patronizing. It
basically says, you know what, in order to allow me to do
business with you and not to view you as an עובד עבודה
זרה, oved avoda zara, I'm going to say that even though you
take your religion very seriously and you're very pious, you're really just
going through the motions and you're really not sincere about what you're
doing, and therefore I can treat you as, I can sort of
still treat the religion as off limits, and you know, Christianity is
still taboo for Jews, but you as a Christian, I don't have
to treat you as off limits because I can sort of say
that you're just going, you know, like מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם minhag avoteihem
bi'yedeihem is a phrase that תוספות Tosfos uses. You know, you're just
doing the way you were brought up. Okay? Where the irony is
is that in the time of the Middle Ages, if a Christian
wasn't being a פרום frum Christian, it was because they were still
being a pagan. You know, so how much did Christianity take root
and how much was the paganism still there? But תוספות Tosfos chooses
to frame it that way, and that's important because that drives a
wedge between Christianity and Christians and allows for increasing, you know, lowering
of boundaries in terms of interactions with Christians. So if you take
a look, we'll just read that one and then we really have
to get back to the גמרא, Gemara. but this was so juicy
I could not not do it. Okay, he says like this:
second line from the top from the wide lines from the top
of תוספות Tosfos. there from the wide lines. לכך נראה דטעם ההיתר,
Lekach nireh detam haheter, the reason of the permission, is משום—now mishum
this says עכו"ם akum but the original
גרסא girsa clearly was either גויים goyim or
נוצרים—שבינינו, that the Christians or the non-Jews among us, קימלא בגוייהו דלא
פלחו לעבודת כוכבים. kimla beghavaihu delo palchu le'avodat kochavim. We know that
they themselves don't actually worship עבודה זרה, avoda zara, even though their
religion is a religion of עבודה זרה. avoda zara, ומהאי טעמא שדר
ליה רב יהודה Rav Yehuda לרבי יהודה leRabbi Yehuda דשדר קרבנא לאבידן
ביום אידא, Umehai tama shadar leh Rav Yehuda leRabbi Yehuda deshadar korbana
la'Avidan beyom eida, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda sent an offering to this
non-Jew on the holiday, on the pagan holiday, קימלי בגוויה דלא פלח
לעבודת כוכבים. Kimli beghavei delo palach le'avodat kochavim. I know that he
doesn't worship עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So in other places, תוספות Tosfos
says explicitly the idea of מנהג אבותיהם בידיהם. minhag avoteihem bi'yedeihem. You're
just going through the motions. You're doing it because that's the way
you were raised. It's not coming through this real act of worship.
Okay, but to get back to where we were, that was a
bit of a digression, but this is just why so much of
the navigating of the
page. Middle Ages of navigating the Christian world. So where are we?
The משנה Mishnah. has these prohibited things. Why is it prohibited? Either
because the non-Jew is sinning, you don't want to aid and abet
the non-Jew's sin, or because you are aiding the act of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, you yourself are indirectly connecting to an act of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah it's not about their sin, it's about your
connecting to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Or the third possibility is you
are participating in the excitement and the hustle and bustle of this
sort of pagan culture that surrounds this holiday and again it's not
because of your supporting them, it's because of your connecting to them.
And then תוספות Tosfos raises the question about doing business on Sunday,
and he has a series of different answers, right? One answer is
that yes it's a problem, but because of hatred or cultivating good
relations or not being rude, being polite, etc. certain things are allowed.
Another answer is technically speaking you're not providing them the object that
they need for their acts of worship and gets into interesting questions
about money lending and is that where is that money going? Is
it going directly to the worship or to supporting the priests which
is not so bad? And the third answer is maybe we need
to rethink not whether Christianity is עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, that he's
not prepared to do, but how do we but how we think
about Christians and trying to sort of put a wedge between Christians
and Christianity that will allow us greater forms of
interaction. Yes. Yeah they basically say yeah I understand it's a bit
it's a bit of a fiction like a legal fiction. It's a
that's clearly a legal fiction but it allowed for a lot of
lowering of restrictions and more interaction. Now again I can't resist I'll
say one other thing about lending because the end of that תוספות
talks about lending money and we know the Jews were into money
lending. So look at the next תוספות. He says להלוותם lehalvosam you're
not allowed to lend them money. Here's another way in which they
gave them they they made gave themselves more allowance. פירש רבינו תם
דוקא בחינם peireish Rabbeinu Tam davka bechinam
it's only you can't lend them money if you're not charging interest.
אבל בריבית שרי aval beribis shari
oh but you're allowed to lend them money if you charge interest
right on you know before and on their holiday. משום דמיצטער טובא
mishum demitzta'er tuva
because that actually causes them a lot of anger it doesn't cause
them joy. So this becomes now a way in which we can
continue to lend money up the the period leading up to and
on their
holidays. ואפילו לפרוע מהם va'afillu lifro'a meihem how about if we have
an opportunity to collect their outstanding debts on our holidays? Right well
you're not supposed to do that but you know maybe that money
will maybe that'll be a loss. So you look at תוספות לפרוע
מהם lifro'a meihem and he says דבגמרא פסקינן כרבי יהושע בן קרחה
דמלווה אטו נפרעין מהם devag'mara pas'kinan k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha demalve atu
nifra'in meihem if there's no document you can collect מפני שהוא כמציל
מידם mipnei shehu k'matzil miyadam because you're saving yourself from a what
would be a loss if you don't have any documentation. ויכול להיות
דאפילו מלווה בשטר נמי נפרעין מהם veyachol lihyos de'afillu malve beshtar nami
nifra'in meihem
maybe even if you have a document and you're not so afraid
it'll get lost you can still collect because you know maybe next
time they won't have the money. Okay he goes on and on.
So basically these two תוספותים Tosfosim are basically other ways of dealing
with certain realities. Yes we lend money so what we're going to
stop lending money on their holidays? Your previous one was about doing
business this is about lending money. Oh no if you lend with
interest that's okay. All right how about collecting money? You're not supposed
to collect. Ah no you're allowed to collect because otherwise you might
lose out that money. Okay so now we've made it possible to
both do buying and selling and to lend and to lend your
money and collect your loans you know all through their holidays. Okay
so giving you a certain sense of dealing with the realities of
life תוספות lived in and what's going on in the גמרא. Gemara
Let's actually start reading some גמרא Gemara because we haven't even gotten
off the משנה. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this רב
ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel so a debate in רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel.
חד תני אידיהן chad tani aideihen with an א alef וחד תני
עידיהן vechad tani eideihen with an ע. ayin. מאן דתני אידיהן לא
משתבש ומאן דתני עידיהן לא משתבש. man detani aideihen lo mishtabesh uman
detani eideihen lo mishtabesh. The one who says it with an א
alef isn't making a mistake and the one who says it with
an ע ayin isn't making a mistake. מאן דתני אידיהן לא משתבש
man detani aideihen lo mishtabesh דכתיב dechsiv דכתיב כי קרוב יום אידם
dechsiv ki karov yom eidam the day of their downfall of the
foreign gods is close. So
the word איד eid means a tragic day. So therefore we're this
is again there's a word for this the opposite of euphemism which
is using a negative word to describe something. Anyway anyway so we're
describing their holidays as the days of their destruction the days of
their downfall because we're sort of you know this is a way
of how do you deal with talking to you know a community
here that's living in this pagan culture the non-Jews and the pagans
seem to have you know successful and you know be reigning supreme
and you're the oppressed people. So you know way of dealing with
it is you you know are constantly sort of you use this
type of a language to give yourself hope and encouragement you know
whatever. So okay so we're going to refer to the holidays as
the days of their destruction. You know it's so funny the way
people sometimes assume that we're using negative terms like Christianity everybody knows
what's the like Yiddish term for referring to Christian I mean not
Christianity Christmas is Christmas Eve. ניטל נאכט, Nittel Nacht, right? So people
assume what ניטל נאכט Nittel Nacht means is ניטל Nittel like the
sanctity was removed from it. Actually what the word ניטל נאכט Nittel
Nacht is, נאכט Nacht is night, ניטל Nittel means is Nativity. It’s
the night of the birth, Natal, like prenatal, anyway. So anyway, okay,
but we’re used to using negative terms for referring to those types
of things. When it refers to houses of worships of other religions
in the Middle Ages, it’s often referred to as בית תפלותם Beit
Tiflotam as opposed to
תפילותם, Tfilotam, their positive prayers, is תפלותם Tiflotam the house of their
nonsense. So you know there’s this way of, which you can you
know understand from a minority oppressed religion dealing with you know the
powerful, other you know non-Jewish
or you know whatever culture that is you know of this other
religion. Okay so anyway so that’s one explanation אידיהם edeihem means the
days of their downfall.
ומאן דתני עידיהם uman de-tani edeihem with an ayin לא משתבש lo
mishtabeish is not making a mistake, דכתיב יתנו עידיהם ויצדקו. de-ketiv yitnu
edeihem ve-yitzdaku. Let them, them the you know foreign gods, these pagan
gods, give their testimony to try to justify the acts of their
worshippers, you know this is in the future time that they’ll say
you know let them testify for their worshippers, they’ll testify their worshippers
worship of them and worship of עבודה זרה and that’s why their
worshippers will be judged in the you know in the future time.
So it’s also sort of suggesting something bad, you know it’s like
they it’s testimony that they are worshipping עבודה זרה. Okay, ומאן דתני
אידיהם uman de-tani edeihem מאי טעמא לא תני עידיהם? mai ta'ama lo
tani edeihem? If you have the aleph why don’t you have the
why did you choose not to have the version with the ayin?
אמר לך תברא עדיף, amar lakh tavra adif, I’d rather explicitly talk
about their downfall, their destruction. ומאן דתני עידיהם uman de-tani edeihem מאי
טעמא לא תני אידיהם? mai ta'ama lo tani edeihem? So if you
have your ayin why not use it with the aleph? אמר לך
מאן קגרים להו תברא, amar lakh man ka garim lehu tavra, what
is going to cause their downfall and destruction, עדות שיהיו בעצמם, eidut
she-yihyu be-atzmam, the fact that they are essentially the testimony, the way
they are you know bearing evidence against themselves, the fact that their
acts show that they are you know worshipping עבודה זרה, that ultimately
is the source of their downfall. The testimony they bring against themselves.
הלכך עדות עדיפא, hilkhakh eidut adifa, I’d rather sort of refer to
it as the day that they are testifying to their pagan identity,
you know that’s what that’s sort of that’s going to come up
to sort of that’s going to be the evidence against them. Okay
והאי יתנו עידיהם ויצדקו בעובדי כוכבים כתיב, ve-hai yitnu edeihem ve-yitzdaku be-ovdei
kokhavim ketiv, is that referring to the idolaters the testimony will be
brought against them? הא בישראל כתיב, ha be-Yisrael ketiv, it’s referring to
Jews. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי כל מצות שישראל עושים בעולם הזה,
amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi kol mitzvot she-Yisrael osim ba-olam ha-zeh, all
mitzvot that we do in this world, באות ומעידות להם לעולם הבא,
ba'ot u-ma'idot lahem le-olam ha-ba, it sort of like what is that
idea when you do a good deed you create an angel right,
every mitzvah that you do will come and testify on your behalf
in the world to come. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, I don’t think that was
a Jewish idea the angel thing, שנאמר יתנו עידיהם ויצדקו, she-ne'emar yitnu
edeihem ve-yitzdaku, they will give their testimony and they will be found
righteous. So that’s not like saying you know let them give their
testimony and try to prove their righteousness you know referring to the
non-Jews, it’s referring to the Jews. They will bring their testimony and
be righteous about all the mitzvot that they did. אלו ישראל, elu
Yisrael, this is Yisrael. And the end of the verse is וישמעו
ויאמרו אמת, ve-yishme'u ve-yomru emet, they will hear and they will say
this is truth. אלו עובדי כוכבים, elu ovdei kokhavim, when the pagans
see all of the mitzvot that the Jews have done and that
the Jews have lived a righteous life they will be forced to
admit you know against their own interest ah that is the truth.
We have been following a life of falseness, they have been you
know that is the truth. So that’s how the verse is being
read that the end of it is referring to the pagans but
not the beginning of it. אלא אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
מאן דאמר אידיהם מהכא, ella amar Rav Huna berei de-Rav Yehoshua man
de-amar edeihem me-hakha, the word אידיהם edeihem comes from the following verse.
יוצרי פסל כולם תהו, yotzrei fesel kullam tohu, the fashioners of the
idol it’s all you know vanities, וחמודיהם בל יועילו, va-hamudeihem bal yo'ilu,
their desired things are will be of no benefit to them, ועידיהם
המה, ve-edeihem heima, it is their testimony. So what does that mean?
It means that basically the same idea, it will testify the things
that they are worshipping won't help them and actually those idols that
they are worshipping in the end will come and testify against them
about their idolatry. So the same idea just based on a different
verse. Okay דרש רבי חנינא בר פפא ואיתימא רבי שמלאי לעתיד לבוא,
darash Rabbi Hanina bar Papa ve-itima Rabbi Simlai la-atid la-vo, in the
future time because this is always where we’re going right, that the
Jews will be shown to be righteous, the non-Jews their idolatry will
testify against them. So now we’re going to elaborate on this. לעתיד
לבוא, la-atid la-vo, in the future time, מביא הקדוש ברוך הוא ספר
תורה ומניחה בחיקו, meivi HaKadosh Barukh Hu sefer Torah u-menihah be-heiko, God
will bring a ספר תורה sefer Torah and put it in His
chest, in His bosom, ואומר and say למי שעסק בה יבוא ויטול
שכרו, le-mi she-asak bah yavo ve-yitol skharo, anybody who has spent time
involving themselves in the תורה Torah here it is in the future
time let them come
and receive their reward. Okay מיד, mi-yad, so of course obviously you
say okay that means the Jews but no look at these non-Jews,
they think they want to try to get their rewards, so they
you know even though they did not live that type of a
life. מתגבשין בהם דוכטורין וערבוביא *misgabshin bahem dukhturin ve-irvuvya*. All the non-Jews
come all mixed up together and everybody's running to try to claim
somehow they deserve this שנאמר shenemar *Shene'emar* כל הגוים נקבצו יחדו *Kol
hagoyim nikbetzu yachdav*. All of the nations are gathered together like they're
all mixed up together. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא amar lahem hakadosh
baruch hu, *Amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu*. God says to them אל
תכנסו לפני בערבוביא *Al tikanesu lefanai be-irvuvya*. Don't come all mixed up.
אלא תכנס כל אומה ואומה וסופריה *Ela tikanes kol uma va-uma ve-sofreha*.
Every nation should come separate with its own wise people, let's look
at each nation differently, which is actually a nice point, you know,
because sometimes non-Jews, sometimes Jews look at all non-Jews of like one
thing. Oh, non-Jews are X. You know, it's a classic type of
an attitude, right? When you sort of, you know, what's it called,
what's the word, when you paint everybody with one brush. Not generalize,
what, what? Stereotype, right. When you sort of stereotype or, you know,
you have those types of attitudes, right, so you sort of, so
anyway, so you know, like all non-Jews are this thing, all non-Jews
are X. The same way people say like all Jews are X,
right, sort of like you know. So here, what's interesting is not
just that as individuals, you know, like with all people, some are
righteous, some are wicked, some are mean, some are nice, or whatever,
but actually using this as an opportunity to try to sort of
characterize different nations, different non-Jewish nations, different peoples. So I guess there's
still some generalizing and stereotyping going on, but at least it's not
saying that they're all the same. Whatever, let's look at them distinctly,
okay. שנאמר *Shene'emar* ויאספו לאומים *Veyasefu le-umim*. The nations gathered. ואין לאום
אלא מלכות *Ve-ein le-um ela malchut*, and that means kingdom like a
national identity. שנאמר *Shene'emar* ולאום מלאום יאמץ *U-le'um mi-le'um ye-ematz*, one nation
against another will strive. ומי איכא ערבוביא קמי הקדוש ברוך הוא *U-mi
ika irvuvya kamey hakadosh baruch hu*? Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interrupts.
It's very interesting because this is like a long ברייתא *Braita*, but
there are these Aramaic interruptions where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of,
you know, has like basically interrupts the flow to say wait, I
got a question here. ומי איכא ערבוביא קמי הקדוש ברוך הוא *U-mi
ika irvuvya kamey hakadosh baruch hu*? One minute. Things aren't confused before
God, even if everybody showed up together, whatever it means everybody, like
are we imagining the resurrected people, are we imagining their souls, that's
not exactly clear. But anyway, God definitely can sort of, you know,
distinguish them. So אלא כי היכי דלא לערבבו אינהו בהדי הדדי *Ela
ki heichi dela le'irvevu inhu bahadi hadadi*. No, it's not for God's
sake, it's for their sake, that they shouldn't be mixed up with
one another דלישמעו מאי דאמר להו *Delishme'u mai de-amar lehu*, that they,
each separate nation, should be able to focus on what God has
to say to them. So God doesn't need it, but they need
it. So anyway, let's keep on going. I know it's already 8:30,
but let's go a few more minutes. מיד נכנסה לפניו מלכות רומי
תחלה *Miyad nichnesa lefanai malchut romi techila*. So the Roman kingdom comes
first before God. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*? Okay, notice the shift to
Aramaic. That's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* inserting these explanatory or you know
types of lines. Why does Rome go first? משום דחשיבא *Mishum de-chashiva*.
Because it's the most important. ומנלן דחשיבא *U-menalan de-chashiva*? How do you
know it's important? דכתיב *De-chtiv* ותאכל כל ארעא ותדושנה ותדקנה *Ve-tochal kol
ar-a ve-tedushena ve-tedukena*. This is by the vision of Daniel. It ate
the whole land and it trampled it and it whatever, crushed it.
אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*. And Rabbi Yochanan says זו רומי
חייבת *Zu romi chayavet*. This is the wicked Rome שטבעה יצא בכל
העולם *She-tiv-ah yatza be-chol ha-olam*, that its, its sort of its imprint,
you know, has gone out throughout the whole world, that its reputation
spreads and its power spreads throughout the whole world. So Rome, so
evil Rome goes first. Okay. ומנלן דמאן דחשיב עייל ברישא *U-menalan de-man
de-chashiv ayel be-reisha*? How do you know the more important person goes
in first to be judged by God? כדרב חסדא *Ke-de-rav Chisda*. Like
Rav Chisda. דאמר רב חסדא *De-amar Rav Chisda*. Again, this is all
a digression here. דאמר רב חסדא מלך וציבור מלך נכנס תחילה לדין
*De-amar Rav Chisda melech ve-tzibur melech nichnas techila la-din*. If a king
and the nation is coming to be judged by God, the king
goes in first שנאמר *Shene'emar* לעשות משפט עבדו ומשפט עמו ישראל *La'asot
mishpat avdo u-mishpat amo yisrael*, to do the judgment of His servant
and the judgment of His nation Israel. Okay, so first God judges
the king and then God's servant, I guess, and then God judges
the nation. וטעמא מאי *Ve-ta'ama mai*? Why? איבעית אימא לאו אורח ארעא
למיתב מלכא מאבראי *I-ba'it eima lav orach ar-a le-meitiv malka me-avrai*. Either
it's not respectful for the king to stand outside. So it's very
funny, like standing outside, are we talking about people, like you know,
how exactly is it imagining this, but okay, so you know, an
honored person goes in first. So that's number one. ואיבעית אימא *Ve-i-ba'it
eima*, or if you want you say מקמי דליפוש חרון אף *Mikamei
de-lifosh charon af*. Before God gets too angry, right? So because since
we're going to be dealing with everybody's sins, you want to be
the first person in before God is getting really frustrated by all
of the sins that God has been looking at and reviewing. So
if you're the first one in, maybe you'll get off a little
bit easier. Now, that both of that is very funny. That could
explain why if we're thinking about God judging the Jewish king, you
know, and then judging the nation, right? Why why that would be
first, because you want to go nicer on the king, you want
to respect it. But how do you apply that to the idea
of judging the wicked Roman government? Right? So I mean, it's just
like Rome is wicked and so on. So what, you want to
show them the respect? Maybe you want to say, yeah, even though
they're wicked, if they're the most powerful, sometimes you've got to respect
the person in power. But what, you want to say God, you
don't want God to be as angry at them? They get to
go first so God is less angry at the Romans? So like
the it doesn't exactly connect. Obviously this is like a digression. We're
using another... Third דרשה *drasha* that we have about kings and a
king, a Jewish king, and judging ישראל *Yisrael* and somehow just borrowing
it even though the dots don't exactly connect. Okay, let's just read
a little bit more about this, get to see what that interaction
is, going back to this interaction. So God says, okay, אמר להם
הקדוש ברוך הוא amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu, *Amar Lahem HaKadosh Baruch
Hu*. Now we're back to the actual sort of פסוק *pasuk*. God
says to them, במאי עסקתם bemai asaktam, *Bemai Asaktem*? What have you
guys done in the course of your, you know, history on this
earth, you Romans, you know, now that it's coming to the end
of days? What have you done? אומרים לפניו omrim lefanav, *Omerim Lefanav*,
they say to him, רבונו של עולם ribbono shel olam, *Ribbono Shel
Olam*, Master of the Universe, we've done a lot to make this
world a better place. הרבה שווקים תקנינו *Harbe Shvakim Tikninu*, we made
many marketplaces. הרבה מרחצאות עשינו *Harbe Merchata'ot Asinu*, we've made many bathhouses.
הרבה כסף וזהב הרבינו *Harbe Kesef VeZahav Hirbinu*, we've increased gold and
silver, you know, we've amassed a lot of wealth and so we've
actually created, you know, like a nice, wealthy culture, a good economy.
So we've done a lot that we deserve credit for. וכולם לא
עשינו אלא בשביל ישראל vechulam lo asinu ela bishvil yisrael, *Vekulam Lo
Asinu Ela Bishvil Yisrael*, and our all intent and all of this
was to help the Jewish people. Okay, maybe that was a little
bit of an... I knew that you were going good, this is
a little bit of an overstatement. כדי שיעסקו בתורה *Kedei Sheya'asku BaTorah*,
so that we just wanted why we deserve a reward, because we
helped them in their תורה Torah *Torah*. We made such a good
economy and a society and that lets people spend time learning תורה
Torah. *Torah*. You know, that's why we invented, you know, cars and
electricity or whatever so people could just have more time, free time
to study תורה Torah? *Torah*. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Lahem
HaKadosh Baruch Hu*, God says to them, שוטים שבעולם *Shotim SheBa'olam*, idiots!
כל מה שעשיתם לצורך עצמכם עשיתם *Kol Ma She'asitem Letzorech Atzmechem Asitem*,
you all doing it for your own sake. תקנתם שווקים להושיב בהן
זונות *Tikantem Shvakim Lehoshib Bahen Zonot*, you made marketplaces just for your
prostitutes. תוספות *Tosafot* points out actually there was some other reasons to
make it, just because they're doing it for self-interest doesn't mean you
have to talk about them about supporting, you know, prostitution, but okay,
we're looking for a good reason to knock on them, so we're
going to mention that. מרחצאות לעדן בהם עצמכם *Merchata'ot Le'aden Bahem Atzmechem*,
your bathhouses were just for your own, sort of, indulgence. כסף וזהב
שלי הוא *Kesef VeZahav Sheli Hu*. Oh, you think that you created
such a good economy and there's all this gold and silver? That
all comes from me, שנאמר לי הכסף ולי הזהב נאם ה' צבאות
*Shene'emar Li HaKesef VeLi HaZahav Ne'um Hashem Tzeva'ot*. Okay, so it's interesting,
he could have said also you did it for yourselves, but the
point is you want to sort of end like, and here's the
important point I want to sort of say which is going on
in this. Not only is it saying, oh, they're going to get
punished, but part of this as I said is a whole question,
the question to be asking throughout this is, what is this telling
you about how we are choosing to see, how we see or
we choose to see the larger world? Do we look around us
and see, oh, those wicked non-Jews, you know, there's such שמוץ *shmutz*
out there and it's all, all this stuff that's against our Jewish
values? Or do we say, you know, we are so, we are
so blessed to be benefiting from living in this society in all
the amazing ways in which, you know, and everything that we've gained
from this society we should be deeply grateful, right? So here, what
you're actually doing is you're presenting, look at, there's a claim to
be made. The claim to be made is, is that, you know,
what the Romans did with all, whatever they might have oppressed the
Jews or whatever, they actually made it a better world and they
made it better society and that maybe even helped us learning תורה
*Torah*. Now, the problem, so it's being put out there, the problem,
not the problem, the issue about this, this דרשה *drasha* is that
it's not, it's, it's putting it out there to reject it. It's
not putting it out there in order to say we actually owe
them credit, right? Because if they would have said we didn't do
it for the sake of ישראל *Yisrael*, we did it for our
own sake, but we deserve some credit that we were did help
them, you know, them through this even though that wasn't our intent,
right? But that wouldn't serve the purposes of this מדרש midrash. *midrash*,
because then actually we would have to give them credit. So the
מדרש midrash, *midrash* actually says they want credit for doing it for
their sake, for our sake, and that's how they get rejected. Now,
you didn't do it for, you don't deserve credit, right? But it's
sort of, now how about the sort of, the fact that we're
still left with this lingering thought which is, okay, maybe they didn't
do it for our sake, they did it for their sake, but
we did benefit from it? So that's the end which is says
God says, it's all me anyway, לי הכסף ולי הזהב *Li HaKesef
VeLi HaZahav*. Don't take credit for anything, whatever your intent was, this
is all coming from me, right? So this מדרש midrash, *midrash* is
interesting because it's structured specifically on the one hand to deal with
the possible claim that we can actually be grateful and recognize the
accomplishments of the larger world and actually appreciate how that's helped us,
but it's being framed in a way which is, no, don't give
any credit to that, they did it for themselves and anyway it
all comes from God. Alright, so let's just read, I know it's
already late, but let's just read one more sentence about this, okay,
to see how this applies to one more nation and then we'll
end with that for now. Okay, כלום יש בכם מגיד זאת klum
yesh bachem magid zot? *Klum Yesh Bachem Magid Zot*, is there anybody
who can say this, שנאמר מי בכם יגיד זאת shenemar mi bachem
yagid zot. *Shene'emar Mi Bachem Yagid Zot*? That's the end of the
verse that all the nations gather, the end of the verse says,
it's all a דרשה *drasha* on the פסוק *pasuk*. All the nations
come before God, they... rather, who among them can say this? So
what's the this? ואין זאת אלא תורה ve'ein zot ela Torah. שנאמר
וזאת התורה אשר שם משה. shenemar vezot hatorah asher sam moshe. None
of you actually have real תורה and don't even say you aided
Israel in their תורה. No, that was also for your own interest.
מיד יצאו בפחי נפש, miyad yatzeu befachi nefesh, they go despondent. יצתה
מלכות רומי, yatzta malchus romi, so Rome leaves, ונכנסה מלכות פרס venichnesa
malchus paras and the Persian government comes in אחריה. achareha. So now
the גמרא says מאי טעמא דהא חשיבא בתרה, mai ta'ama deha chashiva
basra, why does Persia come next? Because they were next in level
of importance. ומנין דכתיב, umaniyan dichtiv, the vision of דניאל Daniel is
all inserted into this מדרש. וארו חיוה אחרי תנינא va'aru chiva acharei
tinyana and then came a second beast, דמיא לדוב, damya ledov, like
a bear. There, I get a mention in this. But I'm not
sure it's a good mention. דתני רב יוסף, detani Rav Yosef, אלו
פרסיים שאוכלין ושותין כדוב, elu parsiim she'ochlin veshosin kedov, these are the
Persians who eat and drink like a bear. This is not a
compliment. ומסובלין בבשר כדוב, umesubalin bavasar kedov, they're like fleshy with, you
know, they're layered with flesh like a bear. ומגדלין שער כדוב, umegadlin
se'ar kedov, they're hairy like a bear. ואין להם מנוחה כדוב, ve'ein
lahem menucha kedov, and they're constantly stirring around and they're never at
peace, like a bear. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא, anyway, Elman has
a whole thing about why this was used as a whole derogatory
statement about Persians. Anyway, אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא, back to the
מדרש, God says to them, במאי עסקתם, what have you involved yourselves
in? אמרו לפניו רבונו של עולם, ameru lefanav ribbono shel olam, הרבה
גשרים גשרנו, harbe gisharim gisharnu, we've built many bridges, הרבה כרכים כבשנו,
harbe krachim kavashnu, we've conquered many cities, הרבה מלחמות עשינו, harbe milchamos
asinu, we've made many wars. I don't know why that's a good
thing to conquer cities and make wars. וכולם לא עשינו אלא בשביל
ישראל, we all did it for the sake of the Jewish people,
כדי שיתעסקו בתורה, kedai sheyitasqu batorah, so that they should occupy themselves
with the Torah. אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא כל מה שעשיתם לצורך
עצמכם עשיתם, amar lahem hakadosh baruch hu kol mah she'asitem letzorech atzmechem
asitem, it was all for your own sake. גשרתם גשרים ליטול מהם
מכס, gishartem gisharim litol mehem meches, the bridges are to collect tax.
כרכים לעשות בהם אנגריא, krachim la'asot bahem angariya, you conquered cities in
order that you should be able to draft people to the king's
service. מלחמות אני עשיתי, milchamos ani asiti, anyway, it's all for me,
שנאמר ה' איש מלחמה. shenemar Hashem ish milchama. כלום יש בכם מגיד
זאת? zot? Do you have anybody that can say זאת? שנאמר מי
בכם יגיד זאת. ואין זאת אלא תורה. Does any of you really
have a claim to the תורה? שנאמר וזאת התורה אשר שם משה.
vezot hatorah asher sam moshe. מיד יצאו מלפניו בפחי נפש, miyad yatzeu
milfanav befachi nefesh, they basically, they also left despondent. דכיון דחזיא מלכות
פרס, dekivan dechazya malchus paras, the גמרא again interjects, once Persia saw
למלכות רומי דלא מהני ולא מידי lemalchus romi dela mahni velo midi
that Rome didn't succeed in its claims, מאי טעמא עיילה, mai ta'ama
ayila, why did Persia think they would do any better with their
claims? אמרי אינהו סתרי בית המקדש, amri inhu satrei beis hamikdash, the
Romans destroyed the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so they're coming in with
one strike against them. ואנן בנינא, va'anan banina, but we the Persians
let the Jews return and build the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Okay, so that's why they thought they would get a pass. וכן
בכל אומה ואומה, vechen bechol uma va'uma, every nation does the same
thing. Okay, so the גמרא says דכיון דחזי לקמאי דלא מהני ולא
מידי, dekivan dechazi lekamai dela mahni velo midi, so I don't get
it, the other nations, once they saw Rome and Persia didn't get
anywhere, מאי טעמא עיילי, mai ta'ama ayili, why did they think they
would get somewhere? סברי הני אישתעבדו בישראל, savri hanei ishtabdu beyisrael, they
at least subjugate, they subjugated the Jewish people, ואנן לא אישתעבדנו בישראל,
va'anan lo ishtabdanu beyisrael, we were just these other nations, China, we
had nothing to do with the Jews, so maybe we should get
credit. Okay, so then the גמרא says מאי שנא הני דחשיבי ומאי
שנא הני דלא חשיבי, mai shena hanei dechashivi vemai shena hanei dela
chashivi, why did we mention Persia and Rome and not the other
nations? משום דהני משכי במלכותייהו עד דאתי משיחא mishum dehanei mashchei bimalchusaihu
ad de'asi meshicha because Rome and Persia will maintain their kingdom, domain
until the משיח Mashiach comes. Those are the most important nations for
all future times, exactly whether that's true or not is a different
question. Anyway, אומרים לפניו, so these other nations say, רבונו של עולם,
so now what are they going to say to God? We're going
to end here because they can't say, look at all this stuff
we did for the sake of the Jewish people, because they didn't
even subjugate the Jewish people, the Jewish people weren't in their lands,
so their claim is going to be a different claim. Okay, so
we'll pick up with this tomorrow, but basically we've seen that the
claims are, you know, if we're living in this society, so again,
this is a question about framing how we're going to look at
the larger society. And for the purpose of this מדרש, it is
to reject any sense of appreciation or gratitude. Yes, they did all
this stuff and yes we benefit from it, but on number one,
they did it all for themselves, and number two, anyway it all
comes from God. Okay, so later we'll see a more positive voice
about this, but this is one that is sort of framed to
reject its importance and for us to sort of appreciate and be
grateful for it,
and certainly to reject the sense that that gives them any claim
to any future reward. Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.